<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The armies vindication of this last change wherein, is plainly demonstrated, the equity, power and right of the army to settle these nations upon the foundations of righteousnesse and freedome : together, with answers to the most material objections made against them.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12936943</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12936943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 730:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The armies vindication of this last change wherein, is plainly demonstrated, the equity, power and right of the army to settle these nations upon the foundations of righteousnesse and freedome : together, with answers to the most material objections made against them.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95774:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95774:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARMIES Vindication of this laſt CHANGE. <hi>WHEREIN,</hi> Is plainly Demonſtrated, the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Power and Right of the Army to ſettle theſe Nations upon the Foundations of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and Freedome. <hi>TOGETHER,</hi> With Anſwers to the moſt material Objections made againſt them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I will alſo make thy Officers Peace, and thy Exactors Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſa. 60. v. 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Publiſhed by ſpecial Command.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Grey-hound</hi> in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95774:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95774:2"/>
            <head>The Armies Vindication of this laſt Change.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He late King by his Writ called the long Parliament, and that not by any voluntary act of his own, but as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereunto, by the coming of the <hi>Scots,</hi> with an Army into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> This Repreſentative thus Convened were the Body of the People, of whom he was Head: But afterward, the King, inſtead of joyning himſelf with this great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell through pretended fears and jealouſies, did moſt unnaturally ſeparate and eſtrange himſelf from it, withdrawing Protection from the People; forfeited all obedience due to him as King: For as much as he betook himſelf to force and acts of open Hoſtility, by ſetting up his Standard, by which he put himſelf into the condition of a private Perſon, laying claim to no more than he could purchaſe to himſelf, by force and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95774:3"/>Military Power: Thus wholly laying aſide his Civill Government, turning it into a Military; at length he, as <hi>Saul,</hi> periſhed by his own ſword, by ſheathing it in the bowels of his own body politick</p>
            <p>By this means the Parliament became poſſeſſors of the Soveraignty, Greatneſs, Honour and riches of the King: whereby there was a plain tranſmitting or tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating of power from the King to the Parliament, the peoples Repreſentatives; who at that time was as a nurſing Mother to ſuccour and tenderly embrace the well-affected, and good people of the Nation: by which means the hearts and affections of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in the land were gathered up to, and went along with them; becauſe they were a Bulwark to keep Tyranny and Oppreſſion from all that did adhear unto them; and gave encouragement and Protection in the external Exerciſe of Religion and the ſervice of God. Theſe things not being forgotten, we cannot but mention the long Parliament with Honour.</p>
            <p>The Parliament not being able to go on in their work without the aſſiſtance of an Army, were forced to make ſeveral Appeals to the people, whoſe Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives they were; and thoſe of them that were well-affected to the cauſe of Religion and Liberty, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly accepted of the Parliaments Call, and did joyn a helping hand by concurrance of their good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and prayers; alſo by their purſes and perſons, to carry on the great work that was on foot. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being thus conſtrained to conſtitute a Military body, different from their own; and to make a Power of much greater force and ſtrength than that which was Civill: The power and greatneſs of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did hereby neceſſarily deſcend into the Army,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95774:3"/>and the good people thus called to their aſſiſtance, and adhearing to them; and they themſelves became a leſſer and more inferiour power, by pouring out and devolving their greatneſs and ſtrength into another Society of men, more formidable than themſelves; and their acting, as it were, in away of ſubſerviency to them; for what conſiderable thing did the Parliament elſe, but to raiſe money for the Army, and ſupply it with ſuch neceſſaries that were ſutable to their work and deſigne.</p>
            <p>The Army being thus taken out of the good people of the land, and united in ſuch a formidable body, obtained great Victories and ſucceſſe; and through the rich mercy and bleſſing of God, overcame all their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies in the three Nations: the King and his party, together with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> were wholly ſubdued. This being done, there was no legall form of civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment left; the King being taken away, both in Perſon and Office, the Houſe of Lords diſſolved: the Soveraignty muſt needs fall into the hands of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; from whence it firſt ſprange: The Kings party, and ſuch as were Neuters having loſt their Right and Priviledge, the good people imbodied in an Army, together with thoſe that adheared to them, muſt of undoubted right, be receptable of all Power and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty: For all greatneſſe and Authority that takes its riſe from the people, when its ſhattered and broken, muſt neceſſarily return thither again, as retyring to its true Centre. As the Sap of a Tree, after it hath put forth it ſelf into the Branches, and comes to be nipt by Winter ſtorms, its courſe is to ſink down again into the root; ſo it fares with all Governments, Honours and greatneſſe in the world, when they are broken and ruined, they diſſolve into their firſt principle and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95774:4"/>
            <p>The principal thing to be cleared is, that the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty ſhould reſolve it ſelf more into the people im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied in an Army, than into the peoples Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives in Parliament.</p>
            <p>To evince this, conſider, that the Parliament had no legall Conſtitution or Right to Government by any law of this Nation, that's moſt evident; the Office and Perſon of the King being taken away, the Houſe of Lords being diſſolved, as I ſaid before: It was not in the power of the Commons (being but a third State in the Government) to Conſtitute themſelves a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, without ſome new act of the people, to make them ſo; unleſſe they had a Power of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves inherent, that they might doe ſuch things as was never intruſted them, by thoſe that choſe them: The Kings Writ calling them, and the Peoples election waxed old, and antiquated, as out of date: And hence their ſtanding as a Government, after the death of the King, was onely as they were upheld by the power and neceſſity of the Army; and when they were of no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe to the Nation, they were by the Army <hi>gently</hi> laid aſide: and the great approbation the people gave to their diſſolution, did clearly recall their former e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, and all further truſt repoſed in them.</p>
            <p>The next thing is to prove, that the Army is the principall body of the People, in whom the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth at preſent reſide. That ſuch a power ſhould naturally deſcend into the Army, and much ſuperiour to that of the Parliament that raiſed them, will appear by all humane and divine reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Members of the Army, for the moſt part of them, were raiſed out of the ordinary and common bulk of the people, which are the greatneſſe and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95774:4"/>ſtrength of the Nation, in whom lies the greateſt, and the moſt common Intereſt of the whole, with all its concernments.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Army were ſuch, as did anſwer the call of the Parliament, when they made their appeal to the people for to judge of their Cauſe: Now to whom I make an appeal, I make him ſuperiour to my ſelf; I ſet him as a Judge and Lord over me; thus did the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by their Declarations to the people, calling upon them to be Judge of their own Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: Theſe of the Army being more valiant than others in the great concernments of the Nation, they have the juſt title of the people of <hi>England,</hi> having interpoſed between the peoples Rights and Liberties, and that ſlaviſh Tyranny that was breaking in upon them.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Army are a conſtitution of more vigor and ſtrength than any other; the Parliament of it ſelf could act but in a low, weak, inconſiderable way; their greateſt Authority lying in the Camp: The Military Sword being alwayes more ſharp, than that of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; more able to do juſtice and to give protection, than any Civil Sword, or inſtituted power could. The Parliament had the <hi>form,</hi> but the Army had the <hi>power</hi> of the higheſt adminiſtration of juſtice, as having more intrinſical and fundamental ſtrength in it, than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; The Malignants felt the power, and by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence know that this is true: Could the Parliament o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the King, beat him out of the field, bring him to tryall and execution, but by the power of an Army? by this its undeniable, that the power of the people thus formed into an Army, are the ſtrongeſt power.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. A Fourth conſideration proper for this, is, that the Army are the people in an active body; not in a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95774:5"/>bulky, heavy, ſluggiſh heap; but the people gathered up into heart and union, filled with ſpirit and life, for work of their generation, very uſefull and active; men of publique ſpirits, carrying the intereſt of the people of God, and the good of the Nation in their aim and eye. To this may be added, the concurrence of the hearts and affections, prayers and good deſires of the honeſt party of the Nation, going along with them; theſe have contributed their beſt aſſiſtance to help them in their progreſs. Although of late, many, partly through weakneſſe and paſſion, or diviſions and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongſt them; and partly from the Armies miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages and apoſtacies, have been offended with them; but when the Lord ſhall blow away theſe miſts, and lead forth the Army in the ways of righteouſneſs, he will lead his people back, to their former hearty concurrence of their affections to, and their prayers for them: As being ſuch in whom the Lord hath treaſured up their great intereſt, with their Lives and Liberties.</p>
            <p n="5">V. There is a peculiar right of Government or power due to them in the Army, in that they have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured their bloud, and have with the Jeopards of their lives, reſcued themſelves and the honeſt party of this Nation from Tyrany; and have purchaſed Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both civill and ſpiritual with the price of bloud; ſo that God and Nature have put Authority into their Hands: The former ſlaviſh Government that denied Liberty to men as men, and to Chriſtians as Chriſtians, being thrown down by them: the priviledg of Rule belongs therefore to honeſt men, as ſuch, and to the Army, as ſuch; by the moſt undoubted Right that can be imaginable.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95774:5"/>
            <p n="6">VI. I ſhall add one thing more, and that is, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of providence, which firſt brought forth the honeſt people of this Nation into a Military body, and that diſtinct from the Civill power: and theſe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with many ſignal Deliverances, Victories, and ſucceſſes; the produce and iſſue whereof doth entitle the Army and honeſt People to the moſt unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Right of Power &amp; Government in theſe Nations: I would not by all this, draw men to adore an Army, or arme of fleſh; but the Lord in the midſt of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whether in the Army, or without; all the Saints in the Land are the Army of God they are publique per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that minde a publick good; and have all one Common intereſt: Theſe are the men God hath deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for Government.</p>
            <p>Thus we may plainly ſee where the Power and Right of Government is ſeated, in the good People; and eſpecially to thoſe in the Army: who was pleaſed to recall the Members of Parliament to a further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing of their Truſt, formerly repoſed in them? this the Army did, at leaſt tolerate or condeſcend unto: though this act of theirs did not proceed ſo much from judgement and wiſdome, as from urgency and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: being toſſed to and fro by the viciſſitudes and changes of things; and being in ſome darkneſs; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at that time no better thing in their eye, they choſe this as the next expedient, hoping ſome good might have been done by them; but ſinding, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of going forward to ſettle the Nation, they were carried on to many precipitate actings, to throw down many things done, in point of Reformation; and not onely ſo, but they went about to deſtroy and alter the whole Conduct of the Army, though they were the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95774:6"/>very legs that bore them up, and the Power that called them together: And when the greateſt part of the Nation was ready to riſe up againſt them, the Army onely did interpoſe by their power to uphold them: Now if the Army had power to gather them, they had alſo power to ſcatter them: for the ſame power that ſets up may pull down; it was no breach of law to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them that ſat by no law; Eſpecially, when their proceedings were Diametrically oppoſite to thoſe ends for which they were called.</p>
            <p>The Army a Military body, ſo owned of God, united in ſtrength and courage, carried forth with juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intentions; ſtanding upon their own feet; being a diſtinct power, raiſed by God, by his immediate power (for it was not the King that called the Parliament, but his neceſſity: neither was it the Parliament that raiſed the Army, but their ſtreights; and both theſe, as the product of providence; and not the intentions of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one or the other of them) If then this Army (being the ordinance and appointment of God, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our Liberties and Lives) ſhould have given back their power to the Parliament, as once the Parliament would have given theirs to the King; it had been the higheſt breach of truſt that could be imaginable both to God and his people: And ſurely the Lord would have brought deliverance ſome other way; and would have left them &amp; their houſes to have been trodden under foot, at the luſts and wills of men; the foot of pride ſhould have trampled on them like mire in the ſtreets.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to Anſwer all the materiall Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (that I can think of) that are made againſt the paſt and preſent proceedings of the Army.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>The firſt is this, The Army owned the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95774:6"/>as the Supream Authority, received Commiſſions from them, and called themſelves their Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Parliament were the Supream Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Nation, <hi>only</hi> as the <hi>Army</hi> did own them ſo; but as the Army did ſet them up, tollerate and condeſcend to their Authority for a time; yet by no act did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm or perpetuate them, nor I believe never intended it. The Army having ſo much of Power and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment devolved upon them, as we have already ſhewen; having the life, the ſpirit, the vertue of all the good People gathered up into a military body, and being of publique ſpirits, for the good of the honeſt intereſt in the Nation: Its beyond queſtion, to ask by what law or Authority the Army could diſſolve the Parliament? they were obedient while they ſet them in Power over them; but when they thought of changing their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they might do it without breach of any law; where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>And had the good People known the bottom of the Parliaments proceedings, and how they were about to eſpouſe a National Intereſt, intending to have thrown the Government upon the ſpirit of the Nation; no queſtion but all unbyaſſed good men in the Nation would have concurred as much with the Army in this laſt breach, as in the former: but here one precipitant action draws on another; and many mens judgments were ſurpriſed in this laſt action of diſſolving the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, more than in the former. But when good men have their eyes open to ſee, that their Lives and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, their ſafety and ſecurity is wrapt up with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Intereſt; as ever the peoples did in King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, No queſtion, but as one piece, as one body, as one ſoule and ſpirit, they will agree to ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95774:7"/>as may beſt ſecure their own ſafety, and the good of the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>That which cauſes men of carnall and earthly minds to rage and fret, and to ſtrive like a Bull in a net becauſe we ſetle not upon a worldly foundation, a Conſtitution that may take in the ſpirit of the Nation, in all its filth and corruption, in all its malignity and enmity, that we may not make up a Heterogeneall body, a mixture of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay:</hi> What were this but to return to Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, to the <hi>Oynions</hi> and <hi>Garlick;</hi> a going back to the houſe of bondage, to be intangled with the cuſtomes and manners of Aegypt: this were but to be brought to the place where we firſt begun; and ſo to ſuffer loſs, yea, all the price of Blood and Treaſure, the fruit of all the Prayers and Teares that have been ſpent; but the way is to go forward; we muſt to <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Land of peace and truth, of righteouſneſs and juſtice, and ſhort of this, we muſt not ſit down.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>In the ſecond place, Some charge the Army of a ſecond Apostacy and back ſliding; which they ſeemed of late to repent off; and that they confeſſed they lost the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God ever ſince they firſt interrupted the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the Preſence of God went a long time with the Actions of the Parliament, this is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all good people, as well as by the Army, and this was one of the grounds of the Armies inviting it to ſit this laſt time: but that they loſt the preſence of God, by breaking the Parliament, or ever ſince they were broken, this was never acknowledged by the Army: they muſt then have been falſ to their own experience; for all know, that the good people did as much rejoyce at the Parliaments firſt breaking, as at any act of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that had been done amongſt us; and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95774:7"/>of God appeared much more in the time of the Little Aſſembly, than in the latter end of the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. But the Apoſtaſies and backſlidings the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my did bewaile, was for dancing after the pipe of a ſingle Perſon, and together therewith eſpouſing a worldly Intereſt; and ſo building up the broken walls of the City <hi>Jericho,</hi> that they made them a Calf in the Wilderneſſe, this was the ſin of the then General and the Army: though moſt of the Army were paſſive, as to the ſetting up of ſuch a Single Power. But the laſt act of Apoſtacy in the Army, was to give a new Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to this Parliament, which was ſo ſignally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned of God and his people long before (not but there were good things, and good men found in it) but what was this, but to return to Aegypt for help: Why doe we ſpeak ſo high for a Parliament, is it not a worldly Conſtitution, a Body ſitted for a King, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Nation, not of the people of God; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very whit as Babyloniſh as Kingſhip it ſelf: at beſt, the moſt of them are men of eſtates, under ſome prudent qualifications. This Conſtitution hath been excellent in its ſeaſon; and while there was life and power in it, we could not but honour it; but that having been the hand that brought us out of Aegypt into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; it muſt die at <hi>mount Nebo,</hi> it cannot carry us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land of Reſt and Settlement; to ſtrive about it, is to raiſe the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to honour a dead Carcaſſe, to repair a broken Idoll, that can no longer be the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the kingdome of Chriſt or his people.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſtaken, as if I had not great reſpects for thoſe Members in this laſt Parliament that were worthy: I ſpeak not againſt their Perſons, but am on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewing the weakneſſe of a worldly Conſtitution: I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95774:8"/>do deſire in my heart, that thoſe who were Members would come a little beyond that old form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and eſpouſe themſelves with the Cauſe they have heretofore managed, and to act under ſuch a Form of Government, that Providence ſhall deſigne, which by love and union may prove much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and ſafe both for them and us.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>Again, its commonly ſaid, that the Army is bound to ſubject to ſuch as raiſe monies and pay them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer hereunto; Its well known, that this Army (for the moſt part of them) took up Arms out of Judgment and Conſcience, and not as a Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Army: but <hi>who goeth a warfare at his</hi> own charge. If the Pay of the Army ſhould make them ſerve the wils and luſts of men, and let go the Intereſt of good men; they could not anſwer the end of their pay; it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the end ſhould commen ſurate the action, and will more doe ſo, than the means can direct to the end: and it is not ſo conſiderable who pays the Army, as for the Army to conſider wherefore they are paid.</p>
            <p>If they keep their eye to the right end, the ſafety and Liberty of honeſt men, this will more crowne their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, then to ſerve the humours of ſuch as pay them. The Malignant, Neuter, and malecontent cry out againſt <hi>Taxes</hi> &amp; <hi>exciſe,</hi> not ſo much from the Burthen of them, as from their enmity againſt the Army: who are as a girdle of ſtrength to the righteous in the Land, and a bank to keep out that ſea of miſery that an inraged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy would inflict upon them. But when ſhall we hear any of theſe men complaine of the corruption of the Courts of Juſtice, or of the oppreſſion of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95774:8"/>Lawyers, <hi>Who ſell the poor for ſhoos and the needy for ſilver:</hi> Little complaint is made of theſe, though I am very confident, they pick as much monies out of the pockets of poor people, as would in a very great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure maintain the Armies in the three Nations: this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion men love and plead for, as being moſt natural to them, as moſt ſuitable to an old corrupt intereſt But I dare ſay, that no honeſt man intereſted in the cauſe of God, and of his people, of an unbyaſſed judgment, of a publick ſpirit, truly minding his own welfare, and the lives and liberties of his brethren, can be againſt convenient pay for the Army: Conſidering they carry themſelves with love and tenderneſs, not Robing nor Plundering thoſe under their power, but defending the rights and properties of all; being under a ſevere diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, they are civill and of good behavour; I ſay no man that is in his right minde, can be againſt their pay, except he be an enemy. It's well known they groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded great neceſſities, to ſave the purſes of the people; &amp; there is the ſame reaſon of their pay, as of their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and both are of an indiſpenſable neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Object. 4. <hi>In the next place, it's ſaid, that be the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Army never ſo good, yet they must not doe the</hi> leaſt evill, <hi>that the</hi> greateſt good <hi>ſhould come thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It's true, we muſt not chuſe the leaſt evill; yet howere evill may cleave to our actions, ſo there may appear to be much weakneſſe and darkneſſe in ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Army, their work being to deſtroy and pull downe, as thoſe that pull down old houſes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but trouble the eyes of the ſtander by; ſo that ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95774:9"/>of their wayes may be accompanied with precipitancy and raſhneſſe; but who is it, that doth not plough with an <hi>Ox</hi> and an <hi>Aſſe</hi> in his beſt ſervices, and doth not ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh his beſt duties with ſome notable defects, <hi>Moſes ſmote the rock twice,</hi> Numb. 20.11. And <hi>Rahab</hi> concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the two ſpies, by telling an <hi>untruth;</hi> yea, and ſhe ſeemed to do it with unfaithfullneſs to her owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; But the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> tells us, ſhe did it by faith, that is, ſhe by warrant of ſome particular revelation received from God, did this, believing that the Lord was the author of the War, was with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Wilderneſſe; and would give them their Land; and therefore God doth cover her defects, and declares it an <hi>Act</hi> of faith. So I believe many in the Army act by faith, believing the Lord will <hi>ſhake all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> untill the <hi>deſire of Nations come;</hi> and hence the Lord will overlook all <hi>irregularityes</hi> and weakneſſes, that mhy cleave to theer actions, in pulling down worldly powers. The men of the world are chiefly offended, becauſe the kingdome of Chriſt is at the very door, its ſo conſpicuous and bright, that it makes men rage and fume, they know not how to reſiſt it, becauſe its unreſiſtable, and they cannot own it, becauſe it ſuits not with the Worlds wiſdome and policy. Its likely to be much rejected of this generation, to whom its firſt offered: Men are pleaſed to view Chriſts kingdome at a diſtance, as the Jews could converſe with Chriſt in types and ſhadows, but when he comes indeed they reject him; ſo will it be with this Generation.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95774:9"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Object.</hi> It is farther urged, that we muſt be ſubject to <hi>eivil powers,</hi> as to the <hi>Ordinance of God: the powers that be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God,</hi> Rom, 13.1. The uſurp'd powers of the Roman Emperour was <hi>ordained of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The anſwer for this is at hand; A <hi>Military</hi> power is us truly an Ordinance of God, as any other, and <hi>ſuperior</hi> to it. The antient Government being irrecoverably loſt: the Army, with the good People in the condition of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, being an Army cloathed with the peace, freedom, and privileges of the good people; this is as rational and as juſt as any other Government, and much better, and moſt ſuitable then any other for us, at this day, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter.</p>
            <p>It's therefore neceſſary for us to know, that a Military power is as much an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, as the Civil, if not more; and the Lord doth as uſually delight to appear in this form of Government as in any other: he is ſtiled the <hi>Lord of Hoſts</hi> very often: he doth alſo manifeſt it in the Creation, caſting his work into the mould of an Army, when he had <hi>finiſhed the heaven and earth, and the Hoſt of them, Gen.</hi> 2.1. In his Providence, he is ſaid to pitch his <hi>Tent</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them that fear him: when he redeems; he comes as a man of War, with his garments <hi>dipt in blood,</hi> Iſu. 9. When he comes to deſtroy Antichriſt, comes with his <hi>Arm es in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> when he comes to <hi>judge,</hi> he comes with <hi>thouſands of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells:</hi> And thus the Lord rejorceth to come forth in a Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cloathing. And therefore know, that an Army is an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of God, appointed by him, as the moſt abſolute &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect power on earth; having the ſubſtance of all Governments contajned in it. This was <hi>Rubens</hi> portion, and 'tis called the <hi>Excellencie of Dignitie, the Excellency of Strength.</hi> Hence, all Governments are called <hi>powers,</hi> and in Scripture, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Sword.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Civil Magiſtrate ſaith, <hi>He bears not the ſword in vain.</hi> By this we ſee the Sword is an Ordinance of God, and muſt be ſubjected unto, as well as Civil power.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Objection.</hi> In the next place it is often demanded; How it was ſuch a hainous <hi>crime</hi> in the King to demand but five
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95774:10"/>Members; and no breach at all in the Army to diſſolve the whole Parlament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is anſwered thus: When the King came to pluck out the Five Members out of the Houſe, he came in a hoſtile manner, in a time of Peace, when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Nation was whole and intire, ſtanding in its full ſtrength and luſter. But now the Act of the Army is quite another thing, the Government being broken and ſhattered, and that remaining part of the Parkament was very lame and defective: and this ſtanding onely by the Armies power, this leſſens the Crime, if not wholly oble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Object.</hi> Another Objection to be removed is this; Did not <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Waller</hi> disband at the command of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament? and why not this Army?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>Earle of Eſſex,</hi> with others, were called in by the <hi>Self-denying Ordinance,</hi> as they were Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament: and the Government was in the ſame condition, as whole, as intire, as when they were firſt ſent out. Beſides, they were not crowned with ſuch victories and ſucceſs, as the Army ſince was; and moreover, there had been never ſuch a breach of Truſt committed by the Parlament, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all thoſe victories; they were about giving all up to the King again, as by the perſonal Treaty was like to be done, and ſo thoſe that had ventured their lives, ſhould have been left to the mercy of an inraged enemy. Upon this the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make their Appeals to the Army, to interpoſe in thoſe concernments. Now if the Army had disbanded at ſuch a time, it would have been to ſubjected their lives and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo dearly purchaſed, to the luſts and deſigns of evill men: all which in conſcience and duty to God and man, they were bound to preſerve.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the caſe of the <hi>Nine Officers</hi> that made the breach now, was quite another thing then that of disbanding; it was by an <hi>Executive</hi> Authority the Parliament took upon them while they owned themſelves to be the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, going about to turn out <hi>Nine</hi> Eminent Officers upon a <hi>Criminal</hi> Account, without any tryal, or ſo much as a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it being a high piece of Injuſtice ſo to do. The old <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95774:10"/>would alwayes labour to ſatisfie any diſſenting Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, before he would diſmiſs him from his Command. If theſe <hi>Nine</hi> had gone off quietly, they ſhould ſuddenly have had more fellow-ſufferers, the deſign being to breake the whole Conduct of the Army, who had as it were a natural Right to their Places, being ſuch as had hazarded their lives, and the like: Now for theſe to have ſuffered themſelves to be thus trodden under foot, and together with themſelves the intereſt of all good people, had been a greater crime then can at this time be laid to their charge.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Object.</hi> In the next place 'tis ſaid by ſome, That if <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> particular <hi>intereſt,</hi> and neceſsity had not ſtirr'd, the <hi>general good,</hi> would not ſo much moved them. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, as to <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> as 'tis mentioned in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. is an Evil, when it is either fixed on wrong object, or runs after a good object inordinately: But <hi>ſelf-love</hi> in its due la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and meaſure, is no ſin, but a virtue rather, becauſe 'tis made the Rule whereby we muſt regulate our love to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf:</hi> If then it be a duty that I love another, it is alſo neceſſary I ſhould love my ſelf. This Principle of <hi>ſelf-love</hi> (duly regulated) is ſo neceſſary, that the World could not ſubſiſt without it; for from the ſame Principle that I love my ſelf, I love ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and if I did not love my ſelf, I would not love man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; for that I love my own fleſh, my life, my good name, and the like, from the ſame principle I com to love the body, the life, the credit of another, ſo that take away Self-love, ſelf-preſervation, and you take away mercy, love and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs out of the World; <hi>No man ever ſo hated his own fleſh,</hi> as to ſuffer it to be trodden down by pride and injuſtice, if it lay in his power to redeem himſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſame may be ſaid of <hi>particulor intereſt,</hi> If any particular intereſt be a prejudice to the whole, I muſt paſs it by; but when it is for the good of the whole, I am bound to ſtick faſt to it. Now 'tis evident, that together with the Intereſt of thoſe <hi>Nine Officers,</hi> with others that ſhare in the Conduct of the Army, lyes wrapt up with it the Intereſt of all honeſt men; for if ſuch as had with the hazard of their lives reſcued the people from ſlavery and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95774:11"/>bondage, ſhould have delivered up their place of Office, which is ſo naturally and providentially their own, &amp; have given up their own with our conquering Sword, into the hands of others, it had been a high breach of truſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the good people of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly; Laſtly, as to an Act drawn forth through <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> it may be very acceptable to God when our Wil is brought to conſent to a neceſsiry; We come to chuſe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, being called thereunto by an Act of <hi>Providence,</hi> ſo that when neceſsities meet with an obediencial frame of heart, neceſsity become a virtue, as we ſay; and obedience thus drawn forth by an Act of Providence, is as acceptable with God as Obedience grounded upon Gods Word. In the laſt of <hi>John</hi> Chriſt tells <hi>Peter</hi> he ſhould <hi>be carried whither he would not.</hi> There was a neceſsity but his Will being drawn forth to meet the Neceſſity, made it acceptable with God. Sometimes, nay often God works greateſt things by mans neceſsities; for as neceſsity hath no law, ſo it needs none, being a Law to its ſelf.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Obj.</hi> In the ninth place, that which is ſtrongly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly oppoſed is, That we ſhould be ruled by the <hi>Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Sword</hi> its true, when it is drawn forth to kil and deſtroy, to <hi>eat fleſh,</hi> and <hi>dring bleod,</hi> 'tis a dark and moſt ſad diſpenſation; but as 'tis onely uſed to keep down inraged, Enemies, and keep off deſtruction, and when it's accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Wiſdom and Goodneſs, with Righteouſneſs and Juſtice, then it comes to be good and deſirable. But what do we ſpeak of a Government by the <hi>Sword?</hi> Is the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world any other? Have not <hi>Emperours, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Commonwalths</hi> their <hi>Militia's</hi> to force obedience when their Civil Sword is contemned, being blunt and dul? Do they not draw the Military Sword, which is far ſharper? Did not the late King draw this Sword to force the <hi>Scots</hi> to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. All the Government of the Sword is but this, That a convenient number of the Forces be kept under pay, to keep down a turbulent Enemy, and to protect honeſt men in their Rights and Liberties, that would live in peace if they could. This is all the Rule of the Sword: Are not the Civil Adminiſtrations of Juſtice kept up and exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us? Is not every man ſecured in his peculiar rights: Since I have mentioned the Sword, I ſhal ſpeak a little of it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95774:11"/>
            <p>Firſt conſider, the Sword is the Original and beginning of all Governments in the world, and is the onely Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Preſervation of them. Whither do Emperors, Kings, or Common-Weelths retire themſelves in caſe of tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and inſurrections, but unto a Military Power, there being onely ſuccour and defence: They cannot in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſubſiſt, but as it were reſolving into their firſt principles, the Sword, from whence they had their firſt riſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider what ſpecial hand of Providence rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Sword firſt: It was not man, but God raiſed up his People into an Army, when they were at peace and quiet. The King being great in Worldly Pomp and Glory, did bend all the force of his Government to oppreſs a poore harmleſs people that could not live in the Nation unleſs they would defile their conſciences, theſe lived as <hi>ſheep among Wolves,</hi> and were as Doves and Lambs; they had no horns to puſh, or hoofs to tread under; they had no ſword to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but were willing to lye down under all their oppreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But the Lord calling forth theſe to war, &amp; that not from a <hi>private</hi> ſpirit, but with the ſtamp of <hi>publike</hi> Authority, the Lord raiſed up their ſpirits, and made them men of War like himſelf, who is ſtiled the <hi>Lord of Hoſt.</hi> The Lord took his people (as he did <hi>David,</hi> from the ſheepfold) to make them men of War, put a mighty ſpirit into them, affording a great manifeſttion of his own preſence, going along with them, before whom all earthly Powers are fallen and broken to pieces. Thus the Lord cloathed himſelf, with <hi>Zeal</hi> as with a garment, and hath indued his people with ſuch Maſculine virtue and ſtrength, that their <hi>Horns</hi> have been as <hi>Iron,</hi> and their <hi>Hoofs</hi> as <hi>Braſs,</hi> whereby they have threſhed the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and the Hills as Chaff. And this hath not been by Might and Power, but by the <hi>ſpirit of the Lord,</hi> it was not an arm of fleſh that could do this, but a Divine preſence, the Word and the Arm of the Lord going along with an Army.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider the neceſsity of an <hi>Army,</hi> and that in theſe reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ancient Hedge of Civil Power is broken down, and mens hearts and minds full of rage and revenge, the army is the onely bridle to reſtrain it, and is as a wall of fire to keep the exhorbitant and beaſtly fury of evil-minded
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95774:12"/>men, that they would exerciſe upon a remant of people, that God would preſerve in the Land.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a time of <hi>breaking,</hi> and pulling down all worldly Conſtitutions: God is ſtaining the <hi>pride of all glory,</hi> and <hi>treading down ſtrength;</hi> for this reaſon God gathers his people into the form of an Army: as he ſaid to his people of old, <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.20. <hi>Thou art my Battle-axe and Weapons of war; with thee will I deſtroy Nations, and break Kingdomes.</hi> And again, <hi>Fear not, thou worm Iacob, and ye men of Iſrael, I will make thee a ſharp threſhing Inſtrument, that hath teeth, and thou ſhalt threſh the Mountains, and beat them ſmall, and make the hills as chaff; thou ſhalt fan them, and the wind ſhall carry them away, and the wilderneſs ſhall ſcatter them, Iſa.</hi> 41.15. The Lord ſeemed to ſleep in former days, ſuffering his people to lie under oppreſſion; but now he awakes, as in <hi>ancient days,</hi> cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Rahad,</hi> and wounding the <hi>Dragon,</hi> breaking the bands, and bringing his people from under <hi>Egyptian</hi> burthens; This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done but by an Army.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, our condition at preſent is not a <hi>fixed Station,</hi> but a poſture of <hi>direct motion;</hi> we are upon our March from <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> from a Land of bondage and darkneſs, to a Land of Liberty and Reſt: Now the Army is a Body of Activity of life and motion, and ſo fit for ſuch a Work; being full of Spirit and vigor, inlarged in love and kindneſs, ſeparated from the old Forms and Cuſtomes of the world; ſo that while the Lord leads us in a troubleſome wilderneſs, in dark and ruff pathes, amidſt wilde beaſts, and enemies on every ſide: How comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table is it to all good people, to be led by the hand of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in the ways of Juſtice and Freedome.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Army, being as the Sword of <hi>Gideon,</hi> before whom three Nations fell, in whom there is Majeſty, Juſtice and Protection; they are engaged to diſpoſe and frame an Order of Government for theſe Nations: would not the King and his party, think you, had they prevailed, made his own terms, and that without controul? And have not the Army the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſecure themſelves, their Friends, their Eſtates, Lives and Liberties, by the beſt ſecurity they can poſſibly provide for them: it's reaſon that they which give Protection ſhould give Law: This alſo muſt be done by the Aſsiſtance of an Army.</p>
            <p>That which ſubjects the Army moſt to contempt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95774:12"/>is, that they hardly own that Power that God and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath given them: it being the moſt Superiour, the moſt abſolute in the world: but how can the world own it ſo, when it doth not own it ſelf? this renders it inconſiſting with it's own being, and it's own Actings. This is the true reaſon of preſent Troubles and Perplexities; but let the Army but own it's own Power, and it's own Friends, and it need not to fear it's ſucceſs and happineſs. The Law of the Land, the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliaments, old and rotten Cuſtomes not regarded: Hence thoſe of poor, low and droſsie ſpirits cannot own you, nor love you; but thoſe that can ſee beyond the vail of theſe outward things, that know what true liberty and peace is, and what the Foundations of Righteouſneſs are, theſe know how to have charitable Opinions of you, and your Actings; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be in union with ſuch as theſe, and your Foundation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhaken, by any oppoſition whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Obj.</hi> In the laſt place, many complain, that upon every change we look for much, but the Iſſues &amp; Effects are very little.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We always expect more from men then they are able to give us: as for inſtance; Some think a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> will do the work, becauſe they have been uſefull heretofore; but let any man rightly conſider the Temper of the people, how Malignant ſome, how Neutral others; how divided and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the reſt of men are, at this day, this remedy by Parliament, would prove but a killing diſtemper, it might wound us, but could not cure us. Again, others expect much from <hi>ſuch</hi> &amp; <hi>ſuch</hi> men in the <hi>Army;</hi> but we little conſider how much darkneſs and blindneſs poſſeſſes mens minds, how little knowledge they have of the Kingdom of Chriſt, which is at the very Birth, and no man knows how to give it a deliverance Neither do we well conſider how unfit the world is to receive that which is truly Righteous and good, being froward, ſtubborn and perverſe: <hi>The work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be peace,</hi> only to thoſe that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Righteouſneſs, with love and liking: Now alas, what can we expect more from man, then to be diligent in his place; to exerciſe humane wiſdome, to keep peace, and the like. The beſt Government we can expect from man will be mixt, having ſomething of Chriſt and his Kingdome, and ſomething of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane prudence, and of a worldly concernment. Expect no more then this, and you may not be deceived.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95774:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To conclude, with a word to the Army.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Open your boſomes and hearts to all the people of God in the Land, that ace one with you, in your Cauſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; your ſtrength lies in perfect union with them. <hi>The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of Judah ſhall ſay in their hearts, the inhabitants of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatem ſhall be my ſtrength, in the Lord of Hoſts their God,</hi> Zech. 12.15. <hi>Judah</hi> that had formerly many populous Cities, and great Armies; being now without Walls, and almoſt without Inhabitants: yet even they, ſhall with courage and with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence ſay, the Inhabitauts of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (be they never ſo few or diſpiſed) ſhall be our ſtrength. This alſo will be the ſtrength of the Army, A ſirme Union with the Faithfull. here you can never looſe your Intereſt; he that <hi>will ſave his life ſhall looſe it,</hi> but he that will thus <hi>loeſe his life ſhall ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, and Laſtly, be ſure you make ſome progreſs in your way, by every opportunity: <hi>Wherefore cryeſt thou unto me,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Moſes;</hi> by this queſtion God doth not find fault with his Prayer or Supplication for the people; but rather the Lord doth haſten them to action; <hi>Speak unto the children of Iſrael that they go forward,</hi> ſaith he: and I will fall in with my power, miraculouſly to preſerve my people; and deſtroy their enemies. Then let it be the work of thoſe in power to pluck up <hi>eveoy plant the Father hath</hi> not planted, let no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying intereſt remain; God ſaith to you, as to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>Go up, and poſſeſs the Lond which I have ſword, I will give you.</hi> Go on, reform the Law and Miniſtry, purge all Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, break every Yoke, eaſe all burthens, baniſh all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, releaſe the Priſoner, releeve the poor; Fill the Land with Righteouſneſs, what ever is good, holy, juſt, Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let it be brought forth and exerciſed; and the <hi>Lord your God will go before you, he will fight for you, according to all that he did for you in Egypt.</hi> And <hi>your Enemies ſhall bow at the ſoles of your feet, they ſhall call you the City of the Lord, the Sion, the holy one of Iſrael, Iſa.</hi> 60. You ſee beſides your encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you have reward in your Work.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
